<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2013, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE kh:document SYSTEM "\\voyager\templates\DTDs\LNUK\KnowHow\KnowHow.dtd">
<?Pub EntList mdash reg #8364 #176 #169 #8230 #10003 #x2610 #x2611 #x2612 #x2613?>
<?Pub Inc?>
<kh:document>
  <kh:body>
    <kh:document-title>Establishing habitual residence to secure jurisdiction for divorce (AJ v DM)</kh:document-title>
    <kh:mini-summary>Family analysis: Paulina Sandler, associate at Withers, explains how the court in AJ v DM decided that the wife in that case was not habitually resident in England and Wales because her move was not a pre-planned and purposeful relocation.</kh:mini-summary>
    <core:para><core:emph typestyle="it">AJ v DM</core:emph> [2019] EWHC 702 (Fam), [2019] All ER (D) 136 (Mar)</core:para>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_688382">What are the practical implications of this case?</core:title>
      <core:para>The case of <core:emph typestyle="it">AJ v DM</core:emph> provides an illustration of the legal complications which can arise on separation, for international families, with multiple litigation taking place across borders. It highlights the financial limitations imposed where jurisdiction for divorce in England and Wales is based on one party’s sole domicile, which was a particularly acute issue in this case, which involved negligible capital and a reasonably big income. Here, although Cohen J expressed sympathy with the wife’s predicament, he was unable to bestow jurisdiction where it did not exist.</core:para>
      <?Pub Caret 542?>
      <core:para>Further afield, there were also proceedings in Australia and St Lucia. In Australia, there was jurisdiction for freestanding financial proceedings which could deal with the assets situated there and address the needs, and in St Lucia, while there was no jurisdiction for divorce, the wife had made an application for leave to remove regarding the parties’ child which, if granted, would provide her with the opportunity to re-ignite the array of financial applications in England and Wales that were either not currently available or paused.</core:para>
      <core:para>Meantime, the limitations of the wife’s sole domicile petition may yet be extinguished by Brexit.</core:para>
    </tr:secmain>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_688383">What was the background?</core:title>
      <core:para>The parties were both Australian citizens, the husband having emigrated from Ireland in 2005 and the wife having moved from the UK in 2009. Both also retained their Irish/UK citizenship. They met in Australia in 2014 and were married in 2015. The wife became pregnant in early 2016 and while on holiday in the UK in March 2016, she determined to stay for the duration of her pregnancy. During the following months, the parties split up and the husband tied up his business in Australia and went home to Ireland, so that he could be close to the child, once born.</core:para>
      <core:para>The parties reconciled, and the husband moved to England where the parties took a 12-month lease on a property in Warwickshire. The husband was job hunting and, with the full knowledge and acquiescence of the wife, secured a CEO role based in St Lucia. Although the wife would have preferred to stay in the UK, it was an acceptable compromise being only eight hours away from England instead of 24. It was agreed that they would stay in St Lucia for three years (that being the length of the husband’s contract) and the parties settled into an expatriate family lifestyle.</core:para>
      <core:para>In April 2018, while on a month’s holiday with the parties’ child in England, the wife petitioned for divorce, issued a financial application in Form A and made an application to invoke the wardship jurisdiction for a child arrangements order.  The husband responded with an application for the summary return of the child and in July 2018, the wife ‘threw in her hand’ and returned to St Lucia, where she made an application for leave to remove the parties’ child to England.</core:para>
      <core:para>In the middle of June 2018, the husband initiated an application in the family court in Australia for financial relief. The wife retaliated in England by making further various applications:</core:para>
      <core:list type="bullet">
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>to amend her original petition (which was based on her sole domicile) to rely on indent 2 of Article 3.1(a) of Brussels II bis (‘that the petitioner and respondent were last habitually resident in England and Wales and the petitioner still resides there’)</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>to apply under Schedule 1 to the Children Act 1989 (ChA 1989) for financial provision for the parties’ child</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>for a legal services payment order pursuant to the Matrimonial Causes Act 1973</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
      </core:list>
      <core:para>The judgment dealt with the wife’s application for leave to amend her petition, the husband’s application to stay the financial proceedings brought by the wife in April 2018 and the wife’s application to adjourn both matters until after the determination of her application for leave to remove from St Lucia.</core:para>
    </tr:secmain>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_688384">What did the court decide?</core:title>
      <core:para>Cohen J considered the case law in relation to habitual residence, acknowledging not only that ‘it is far easier to re-establish habitual residence in a country where the party in question has been habitually resident’, but also that the wife’s unhappiness in St Lucia must have impacted on the depths of the roots she had put down there and thus the ease with which they could be pulled up. However, the duration of the parties’ stay in St Lucia was not intended to be brief and they had established a family life there.</core:para>
      <core:para>While in some instances a ‘centre of interest’ can be transferred on the day an intention to remain is crystallised, the case law where this has occurred involves an element of pre-planning and organisation. This was not a pre-planned and purposeful relocation. Cohen J used some memorable phrases (at para [39]):</core:para>
      <core:blockquote>
        <core:para>‘It was the antithesis of that—a lady who, in the course of a holiday, changed her mind. […] I accept that does not mean that every brick has to be in place for a new life in England and Wales, but there were no bricks in place at all here.’</core:para>
      </core:blockquote>
      <core:para>Having concluded that the wife was not habitually resident in England and Wales on the date the petition was lodged, Cohen J was able to side step the question of whether jurisdiction under Article 3 of the Maintenance Regulation 4/2009 was able to circumvent the jurisdictional limitations of the 2nd indent of Article 3 of Brussels II bis when it came to making a needs-based award. A question that may be permanently side-stepped if we leave the EU in the next few months.</core:para>
      <core:para>The wife’s divorce petition remains alive but the financial claims, for the moment, are severely limited. The saving graces for the wife are two-fold. First, Cohen J makes it clear that should the wife be granted leave to remove, she will be able to reignite the ChA 1989, Sch 1 proceedings, which are stayed ‘in cold storage’ and he also secured the husband’s agreement to meet the wife’s costs in all jurisdictions on a pound-for-pound basis, which in turn may necessitate a swift settlement.</core:para>
      <core:para>
        <core:emph typestyle="it">Interviewed by Nicola Laver.</core:emph>
      </core:para>
      <core:para>
        <core:emph typestyle="it">The views expressed by our Legal Analysis interviewees are not necessarily those of the proprietor.</core:emph>
      </core:para>
    </tr:secmain>
  </kh:body>
</kh:document>