<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2013, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE kh:document SYSTEM "\\voyager\templates\DTDs\LNUK\KnowHow\KnowHow.dtd">
<?Pub EntList mdash reg #8364 #176 #169 #8230 #10003 #x2610 #x2611 #x2612 #x2613?>
<?Pub Inc?>
<kh:document xmlns:core="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/core" xmlns:fn="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/fn" xmlns:header="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/header" xmlns:kh="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/kh" xmlns:lnb="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/uk/lnb" xmlns:lnci="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/common/lnci" xmlns:tr="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/tr">
  <kh:body>
    <kh:document-title>AnotherExample Examining the impact of Brexit and UK-wide common frameworks on devolution </kh:document-title>
    <kh:mini-summary>Public Law analysis: Kenneth Campbell QC, MCIArb, advocate at Arnot Manderson Advocates and barrister at Lamb Building, considers the interaction between Brexit and UK devolution, the use of UK-wide common legislative frameworks to maintain harmonisation in the UK market once powers and competences exercised at EU level are repatriated, and the impact for the devolved administrations in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland.</kh:mini-summary>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_687398">How does EU law interact with UK devolution and how does Brexit change this?</core:title>
      <core:para>All three devolution structures in the UK involve interaction with areas of EU law and EU competence, and that interaction is complex. As the UK devolution settlements are asymmetrical, a different range of powers is relevant to Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland.</core:para>
      <core:para>While agriculture, which is common to all three devolved administrations, and in Scotland also fisheries, would be the most high-profile, there are other significant policy areas.</core:para>
      <core:para>
        In an <core:url address="www.gov.uk/government/publications/frameworks-analysis" type="https">exercise</core:url> carried out in 2018 (and later updated in 2019), the UK government attempted to identify those areas of EU law that intersect with devolved competence in each devolved administration. These policy areas were broken down as follows:
      </core:para>
      <core:list type="bullet">
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>49 policy areas where no further action was required</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>82 policy areas where non-legislative common frameworks might be required</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>24 policy areas that were subject to more detailed discussion to explore whether legislative common framework arrangements might be required</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
      </core:list>
      <core:para>In that final group of 24, it is likely that further detailed discussion will be required and future arrangements may include a mixture of reserved and devolved competence.</core:para>
      <core:para>Within that listing, the UK government also identified 12 policy areas that it believes are reserved or excepted in the Northern Ireland Act 1998 (NIA 1998).</core:para>
      <core:para>Some aspects, particularly concerning agriculture, are controversial and involve ongoing discussion with the devolved administrations.</core:para>
    </tr:secmain>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_687399">How does Brexit and the government's approach to legislating for it impact on the UK devolution settlements?</core:title>
      <core:para>
        This was a subject of considerable political controversy during the parliamentary progress of what is now the European Union (Withdrawal) Act 2018 (EU(W)A 2018). In a <core:url address="news.gov.scot/news/eu-withdrawal-bill" type="https">joint statement</core:url>, the First Ministers of Scotland and Wales described the Bill as a ‘power grab’ by the UK government.
      </core:para>
      <core:para>That was founded on concerns about the structure of the Bill and the absence of a definitive consent requirement before UK legislation could be made in some areas of devolved competence, currently exercised in conjunction with EU institutions.</core:para>
      <core:para>Although a number of changes were made to the Bill by the UK government during its parliamentary stages, and ultimately the Welsh Assembly (but not the Scottish Parliament) passed a legislative consent motion, some elements continue to be politically controversial.</core:para>
      <core:para>There is not yet much detail about further proposed legislation intended to regulate competences repatriated from the EU. Thus far, the Agriculture Bill currently before the UK parliament, is the main relevant measure.</core:para>
      <core:para>While there have been ministerial exchanges, there is an element of yet-to-be resolved inter-institutional disagreement between the UK government on the one hand, and the Scottish and Welsh administrations on the other. The Northern Ireland Assembly is not sitting.</core:para>
    </tr:secmain>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_687400">What are the relevant parts of EU(W)A 2018 concerning devolution, devolved legislative powers and UK 'freezing powers’?</core:title>
      <core:para>Each of the UK devolution statutes currently contains a requirement that the devolved legislature may not enact measures incompatible with EU law. EU(W)A 2018, s 12 modifies those provisions, removing the EU competence limitation and creating powers for the UK government to apply, by introducing regulations, a temporary ‘freeze’ on devolved competence in specified areas, subject to the approval of the UK parliament via the draft affirmative scrutiny procedure.</core:para>
      <core:para>The effect of such a ‘freeze’ would be to retain the current parameters of devolved competence in relation to EU law for a period of up to five years while the UK government and devolved administrations work together to design and implement the replacement UK-wide frameworks. The powers to apply the ‘freeze’ will expire two years after exit day.</core:para>
      <core:para>The powers to place a ‘freeze’ on devolved legislative competence are inserted into the relevant devolution statutes by EU(W)A 2018, s 12. Corresponding powers relating to devolved executive competence are inserted into the devolution statutes by EU(W)A 2018, Sch 3, Pt 1.</core:para>
      <core:para>The relevant powers can be found in:</core:para>
      <core:list type="bullet">
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>sections 30A and 57 of the Scotland Act 1998 in relation to, respectively, the Scottish Parliament’s and the Scottish government's competences</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>sections 80 and 109A of the Government of Wales Act 2006 in relation to, respectively, the Welsh government’s and the National Assembly for Wales’ competences</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>NIA 1998, ss 6A and 24 in relation to, respectively, the Northern Ireland Assembly’s and the Northern Ireland ministers’ or departments’ competences</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
      </core:list>
      <core:para>The mechanics of operating this process is controversial. Any such regulations, in their nature, are likely to engage the requirement for consent of devolved institutions (under the Sewel convention), however, this is not a precondition for the operation of the powers under EU(W)A 2018.</core:para>
      <core:para>A further layer of tension is due to the fact that these provisions envisage operation by means of UK secondary legislation, thus offering less scope for scrutiny and the operation of the consent mechanism under the Sewel convention.</core:para>
      <core:para>Before draft regulations are laid before the UK Parliament, the responsible minister must have circulated them to the relevant devolved administration and either the relevant devolved legislature must have made a decision on whether it agrees to the regulations being laid or 40 days must have elapsed without such a decision being made.</core:para>
      <core:para>If draft regulations are laid without the support of the relevant devolved legislature, the UK government must publish a statement explaining why the minister has decided to lay the draft in the absence of consent and must lay before Parliament any statement provided by the relevant devolved administration that explain why consent was not given.</core:para>
    </tr:secmain>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_687401">What are UK-wide common legislative frameworks?</core:title>
      <core:para>
        In a <core:url address="assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/686991/20180307_FINAL__Frameworks_analysis_for_publication_on_9_March_2018.pdf" type="https">provisional analysis</core:url> published by the UK government in March 2018, there were 153 areas of EU law identified that intersected with devolved competence—150 of these policy areas arose in Northern Ireland, 107 in Scotland and 64 in Wales. This provisional analysis also set out an assessment of the areas where the UK government considered there was likely to be a need for continued common rules or ways of working.
      </core:para>
      <core:para>
        Both Scottish and Welsh governments have agreed that common frameworks will continue to be required in some areas. The principles agreed by the <core:url address="assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/652285/Joint_Ministerial_Committee_communique.pdf" type="https">Joint Ministerial Committee</core:url> (EU Negotiations) in October 2017 are relevant in this context.
      </core:para>
      <core:para>They are as follows:</core:para>
      <core:list type="bullet">
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>common frameworks will be established where they are necessary in order to:</core:para>
          <core:sub1list type="bullet">
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>enable the functioning of the UK internal market, while acknowledging policy divergence</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>ensure compliance with international obligations</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>ensure the UK can negotiate, enter into and implement new trade agreements and international treaties</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>enable the management of common resources</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>administer and provide access to justice in cases with a cross-border element</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>safeguard the security of the UK</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
          </core:sub1list>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>common frameworks will respect the devolution settlements and the democratic accountability of the devolved legislatures and will therefore:</core:para>
          <core:sub1list type="bullet">
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>be based on established conventions and practices, including that the competence of the devolved institutions will not normally be adjusted without their consent</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>maintain, as a minimum, equivalent flexibility for tailoring policies to the specific needs of each territory as is afforded by current EU rules</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>lead to a significant increase in decision-making powers for the devolved administrations</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
          </core:sub1list>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>common frameworks will ensure recognition of the economic and social linkages between Northern Ireland and Ireland and that Northern Ireland will be the only part of the UK which shares a land frontier with the EU—they will also adhere to the Belfast Agreement</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
      </core:list>
    </tr:secmain>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_687402">What is the legal and constitutional context for the frameworks?</core:title>
      <core:para>At present, some areas of devolved competence fall within EU policy and legislative competence. That is one of the reasons why the UK devolution structures include limits on executive and legislative powers by reference to EU law. Thus, the UK’s internal market is, in part, facilitated by EU regulation.</core:para>
      <core:para>After the UK exits the EU, the question of regulating the UK internal market becomes a domestic competence, though it is likely that there will remain an overlay of international standards in some areas. There will therefore be a question of managing boundaries between central and devolved authorities. That is one of the matters the common legislative frameworks are intended to address.</core:para>
    </tr:secmain>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_687403">The Cabinet Office has issued guidance and reports on the frameworks—what is the key guidance and what can lawyers learn from it?</core:title>
      <core:para>In terms of EU(W)A 2018, Sch 3, Pt 2, UK ministers are required to produce a report every three months setting out steps which have been taken by the UK government (whether or not in conjunction with devolved administrations) towards implementing arrangements which are to replace any relevant powers or retained EU law restrictions. Ministers are also required to report on regulations under EU(W)A 2018, s 12(9) which have been made in the reporting period.</core:para>
      <core:para>
        Two reports have been produced thus far, covering the periods from <core:url address="assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/755498/EU-Withdrawal-Act-Schedule-3-Report.pdf" type="https">26 June to 25 September 2018</core:url> and from <core:url address="www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-second-european-union-withdrawal-act-and-common-frameworks-report?utm_source=47cc8f4a-e943-4cf4-9a10-8dc84eb2b0a4&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=govuk-notifications&amp;utm_content=immediate" type="https">26 September to 25 December 2018</core:url> (see: LNB News 08/02/2019 27).
      </core:para>
      <core:para>There are few concrete lessons which can be drawn from these reports at this stage.</core:para>
      <core:para>In both reports, the UK government speaks of active collaboration with the devolved administrations, and it has also indicated that it currently does not need to bring forward any regulations under EU(W)A 2018, s 12. It follows that thus far matters have been resolved by administrative harmonisation. There will inevitably come a point when hard legislation is required.</core:para>
    </tr:secmain>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_687404">What are the key legal sectors covered in the 24 priority areas and what progress has been made?</core:title>
      <core:para>It is convenient to set out the 24 priority areas. It will be evident that they can be grouped under the broader headings of agriculture and fisheries, food production and safety, the environment, chemicals, professional services, and public procurement:</core:para>
      <core:list type="bullet">
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>agriculture and fisheries:</core:para>
          <core:sub1list type="bullet">
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>subsidies</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>fertiliser regulation</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>GMO regulation</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>organic farming</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>zootech</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>animal health and traceability</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>animal welfare</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>authorisation and use of pesticide products and the maximum residue levels in food</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>plants, seeds and propagating materials</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>fisheries management and support</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
          </core:sub1list>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>chemicals:</core:para>
          <core:sub1list type="bullet">
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>chemicals regulation, including pesticides</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>regulation of the manufacture, authorisation and sale and use of chemical products primarily through Regulation (EC) 1907/2006 concerning the registration, evaluation, authorisation and restriction of chemicals (REACH)</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>hazardous substances planning</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
          </core:sub1list>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>reciprocal healthcare:</core:para>
          <core:sub1list type="bullet">
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>Regulation (EEC) 1408/71 and Regulation (EC) 883/2004 are the main pieces of EU legislation providing for reciprocal healthcare</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
          </core:sub1list>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>Environment:</core:para>
          <core:sub1list type="bullet">
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>environmental quality, including ozone depleting substances</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>implementation of EU Emissions Trading System</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>waste packaging and product regulations</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
          </core:sub1list>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>food production and safety:</core:para>
          <core:sub1list type="bullet">
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>food and feed safety and hygiene</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>food compositional standards</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>food labelling</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
            <core:sub1listitem>
              <core:para>nutrition health claims, composition and labelling of food</core:para>
            </core:sub1listitem>
          </core:sub1list>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>mutual recognition of professional qualifications</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>public procurement</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
        <core:listitem>
          <core:para>Directive 2006/123/EC on services in the internal market</core:para>
        </core:listitem>
      </core:list>
    </tr:secmain>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_687405">In practice how does Brexit and the introduction of UK-wide common frameworks affect the role and powers of the devolved administrations?</core:title>
      <core:para>Both the Scottish and Welsh governments have signalled their commitment not to create divergent policy in ways that would cut across future frameworks, where it has been agreed they are necessary or where discussion continues.</core:para>
      <core:para>
        Northern Ireland continues to be hamstrung by the lack of devolved government. It is clear from the decision of the Court of Appeal of Northern Ireland in <core:emph typestyle="it">Re Buick's Application for Judicial Review</core:emph> [2018] NICA 26 that there are limits to the work which can be done by civil servants in the absence of an elected ministerial executive.
      </core:para>
      <core:para>The UK government’s response to the problem of absence of elected government in Northern Ireland is discussed below.</core:para>
    </tr:secmain>
    <tr:secmain>
      <core:title id="CITEID_687406">The government is taking specific steps to legislate and prepare on behalf of Northern Ireland. How does this work and who is accountable in the event that any of these decisions are vulnerable to legal challenge?</core:title>
      <core:para>As a result of the litigation discussed above, in the autumn of 2018, the UK government introduced the Northern Ireland (Executive Formation and Exercise of Functions) Bill to parliament. This received Royal Assent on 2 November 2018 and is designed to clarify the exercise of powers by civil servants in the Northern Ireland administration in the absence of elected ministers.</core:para>
      <core:para>The Northern Ireland (Executive Formation and Exercise of Functions) Act 2018 (NI(EFEF)A 2018) does not give any new powers but provides clearer boundaries for the exercise of existing powers in the absence of ministers. It requires supporting guidance which provides a framework for decision-making for Northern Ireland departments when judging if those powers should be used in the absence of ministers. NI(EFEF)A 2018 also enables public appointments to be made in the absence of Northern Ireland ministers, including reconstituting the Northern Ireland policing board.</core:para>
      <core:para>NI(EFEF)A 2018 extends the period contained in NIA 1998 for Northern Ireland ministers to be appointed before the local elections later in 2019. Because ministers were not appointed by 29 June 2017, NIA 1998 requires a further election before an executive can be formed. NI(EFEF)A 2018, s 1 is intended to create a period in which an executive can be formed and talks can take place, by removing that current legal impediment to an executive being formed for a defined period.</core:para>
      <core:para>NI(EFEF)A 2018 also requires that the Secretary of State shall publish guidance about the exercise of departmental functions that includes principles which senior officers in Northern Ireland departments must take into account when deciding whether or not to exercise a function and senior officers of departments are required to have regard to that guidance.</core:para>
      <core:para>
        The <core:url address="assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/754029/Cm9725_Guidance_on_decision-making_for_NI_Dpts.pdf" type="https">guidance</core:url> takes as its starting point the proposition that there are certain decisions that should not be taken in the absence of ministers. Senior officers in departments will be obliged to consider whether there is a public interest in taking a decision rather than deferring it. The government also recognises that, in the absence of an executive, there are some decisions that it should take, such as setting out departmental budget allocations for approval by Parliament to ensure that public services continue to function.
      </core:para>
      <core:para>In addition to this important enabling measure, Parliament has also enacted legislation to authorise raising and spending money in Northern Ireland, namely the Northern Ireland (Regional Rates and Energy) Act 2018 and Northern Ireland (Regional Rates and Energy) Act 2019 as well as the Northern Ireland Budget Act 2017 and the Northern Ireland Budget Act 2018.</core:para>
      <?Pub Caret 137?>
      <core:para>
        While NI(EFEF)A 2018 may have provided a degree of stability in the wake of the <core:emph typestyle="it">Buick</core:emph> case, questions remain. The decision of the UK Supreme Court decision in <core:emph typestyle="it">Attorney General for Northern Ireland's reference of devolution issues to the Supreme Court pursuant to Paragraph 34 of Schedule 10 to the Northern Ireland Act 1998 (No 2) (Northern Ireland)</core:emph> [2019] UKSC 1, [2019] All ER (D) 45 (Jan) indicates the sort of issue which may arise.
      </core:para>
      <core:para>
        That application concerned a challenge to a decision on an infrastructure project, the Supreme Court allowed the challenge to proceed and noted that one of the questions was whether <core:emph typestyle="it">Buick</core:emph> and NI(EFEF)A 2018 had exhausted all the issues which might arise about executive powers. That case is currently pending before the courts in Belfast. It remains to be seen whether similar challenges are made to other executive decisions, but it is certainly possible that these may arise.
      </core:para>
      <core:para>
        <core:emph typestyle="it">Interviewed by Robert Matthews.</core:emph>
      </core:para>
      <core:para>
        <core:emph typestyle="it">The views expressed by our Legal Analysis interviewees are not necessarily those of the proprietor.</core:emph>
      </core:para>
    </tr:secmain>
  </kh:body>
  <kh:related-content type="related-documents">
    <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgovw:96FCFDD3-5F9A-478A-ABE5-9E8EA04A9031">
      <lnci:content>Brexit—overview</lnci:content>
    </lnci:cite>
    <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgovw:BB117253-A160-4BFE-9436-85C250B1DE2A">
      <lnci:content>Parliament and devolution</lnci:content>
    </lnci:cite>
    <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:228D42CB-D66A-49CF-BF9D-F5A81A9DB851">
      <lnci:content>Brexit timeline</lnci:content>
    </lnci:cite>
    <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:11B48F8C-2C20-48E3-8042-575DE445F26D">
      <lnci:content>The process of decision making in Northern Ireland</lnci:content>
    </lnci:cite>
    <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editpractgpn:714CED74-2F69-44F9-9D7F-09562113BB4C">
      <lnci:content>An introduction to devolution in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland</lnci:content>
    </lnci:cite>
    <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:6DC90850-FBD5-4012-9CFD-0F1260ED5F53">
      <lnci:content>European Union (Withdrawal) Act 2018—re-examining the key issues</lnci:content>
    </lnci:cite>
    <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:60C24ACD-07A3-4EBD-9417-C78ED29ACBE7">
      <lnci:content>Brexit Bulletin―preparing the statute book for exit day in Northern Ireland</lnci:content>
    </lnci:cite>
    <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:2620C1FB-041B-4AAE-9C12-6CB6332FB6FE">
      <lnci:content>Exploring the Northern Ireland (Executive Formation and Exercise of Functions) Act 2018 (Part 1)</lnci:content>
    </lnci:cite>
    <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:ABA4EDEC-B791-4028-9BC2-90D49F58D9B5">
      <lnci:content>Exploring the Northern Ireland (Executive Formation and Exercise of Functions) Act 2018 (Part 2)</lnci:content>
    </lnci:cite>
    <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:A957146A-89E4-4E34-ACCC-9A1776D4E138">
      <lnci:content>Decision in the Buick Appeal—implications for government decision-making in NI</lnci:content>
    </lnci:cite>
    <lnci:cite normcite="urn:editnews:A950FE96-A193-420D-B5DF-BFE9B3C9C82C">
      <lnci:content>Supreme Court adjourns devolution issues reference (Attorney General for Northern Ireland’s Reference of Devolution Issues to the Supreme Court pursuant to Paragraph 34 of Schedule 10 to the Northern Ireland Act 1998 (No 2) (Northern Ireland)</lnci:content>
    </lnci:cite>
  </kh:related-content>
</kh:document>